There is a gigantic glacier in the West Antarctic.
It is called the doomsday glacier, because if it crashes into the sea-
-Resiacating coastal cities all over the earth to disappear below the surface.
My name is Anna Wåhlin and I am a professor of oceanography.
We are the first to mapped out what is happening under the surface of thwaites-
It is called the doomsday glacier because the ice is about to melt now-
-And we don't know how fast it will go in the future.
If it goes fast, the earth's water level will rise much faster-
-And it would have very big negative consequences for many.
In order to understand the changes, measurements must be performed under the ice.
The glacier is about 500 m thick and extends far below the surface.
In order to get in there, a self -governing submarine is required.
A robot traveling after a preset program-
-And with sensors maps the ice from below.
-To water samples and scan the environment with sound waves and eco-
-To traveling in a pre -programmed pattern.
At the latest assignment of the RAN
-That the supply of warm water to the glacier is greater than expected.
The researchers have seen large cracks that they suspect go straight through the ice.
This has also been seen with ranks under nearby glaciers.
A glacier tongue formed when hot water melts ice at the seabed-
-And leaves a floating tongue at the surface.
The part of the tongue that meets the bottom is like a dam in a pond.
It is held back by the tongue, which presses against mountains underwater.
If you remove the tongue, it is free for the ice to flow.
If it is likely, the researchers are not sure.
It is possible that a new tongue is created and stops the glacier-
-Do that IS from the land -based part becomes like a new dam.
The laws of physics can help us.
-So our impact on the climate is great.
In 300 years we have increased the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere by almost 50 %-
-And is thus a cause of global warming.
As for Thwaites glacier, Anna Wåhlin belongs to those who believe-
-That it will take time for the doomsday glacier to fall.
The nickname is probably a little exaggerated, at least in the near-time
-But climate change is a problem-
-And we must leave a habitable plane to future generations.
Swedish texture: Per Lundgren Iyuno for UR